The Hood Maker

by Philip K. Dick

“A hood!”

“Somebody with a hood!”

Workers and shoppers hurried down the sidewalk, joining the forming crowd. A sallow-faced youth dropped his bike and raced over. The crowd grew, businessmen in gray coats, tired-faced secretaries, clerks and workmen.

“Get him!” the crowd swarmed forward. “The old man!”

The sallow-faced youth scooped up a rock from the gutter and hurled it. The rock missed the old man, crashing against a store front.

“He’s got a hood, all right!”

“Take it away!”

More rocks fell. The old man gasped in fear, trying to push past two soldiers blocking his way. A rock struck him on the back.

“What you got to hide?” The sallow-faced youth ran up in front of him. “Why you afraid of a probe?”

“He’s got something to hide!” A worker grabbed the old man’s hat. Eager hands groped for the thin metal band around his head.

“Nobody’s got a right to hide!”

The old man fell, sprawling to his hands and knees, umbrella rolling. A clerk caught hold of the hood and tugged. The crowd surged, struggling to get to the metal band. Suddenly the youth gave a cry. He backed off, the hood held up. “I got it! I got it!” He ran to his bike and pedaled off rapidly, gripping the bent hood.

A robot police car pulled up to the curb, siren screaming. Robot cops leaped out, clearing the mob away.

“You hurt?” They helped the old man up.

The old man shook his head, dazed. His glasses hung from one ear. Blood and saliva streaked his face.

“All right.” The cop’s metal fingers released. “Better get off the street. Inside someplace. For your own good.”

Clearance Director Ross pushed the memo plate away. “Another one. I’ll be glad when the Anti-Immunity Bill is passed.”

“Another person wearing a hood—a probe shield. That makes ten in the last forty-eight hours. They’re mailing more out all the time.”

“Mailed, slipped under doors, in pockets, left at desks—countless ways of distribution.”

“If more of them notified us—”

Peters grinned crookedly. “It’s a wonder any of them do. There’s a reason why hoods are sent to these people. They’re not picked out at random.”

“Why are they picked?”

“They have something to hide. Why else would hoods be sent to them?”

“What about those who do notify us?”

“They’re afraid to wear them. They pass the hoods on to us—to avoid suspicion.”

Ross reflected moodily. “I suppose so.”

“An innocent man has no reason to conceal his thoughts. Ninety-nine per cent of the population is glad to have its mind scanned. Most people want to prove their loyalty. But this one per cent is guilty of something.”

Ross opened a manila folder and took out a bent metal band. He studied it intently. “Look at it. Just a strip of some alloy. But it effectively cuts off all probes. The teeps go crazy. It buzzes them when they try to get past. Like a shock.”

“You’ve sent samples to the lab, of course.”

“No. I don’t want any of the lab workers turning out their own hoods. We have trouble enough!”

“Who was this taken from?”

Ross stabbed a button on his desk. “We’ll find out. I’ll have the teep make a report.”

The door melted and a lank sallow-faced youth came into the room. He saw the metal band in Ross’s hand and smiled, a thin, alert smile. “You wanted me?”

Ross studied the youth. Blond hair, blue eyes. An ordinary-looking kid, maybe a college sophomore. But Ross knew better. Ernest Abbud was a telepathic mutant—a teep. One of several hundred employed by Clearance for its loyalty probes.

Before the teeps, loyalty probes had been haphazard. Oaths, examinations, wire-tappings, were not enough. The theory that each person had to prove his loyalty was fine—as a theory. In practice few people could do it. It looked as if the concept of guilty until proved innocent might have to be abandoned and the Roman law restored.

The problem, apparently insoluble, had found its answer in the Madagascar Blast of 2004. Waves of hard radiation had lapped over several thousand troops stationed in the area. Of those who lived, few produced subsequent progeny. But of the several hundred children born to the survivors of the blast, many showed neural characteristics of a radically new kind. A human mutant had come into being—for the first time in thousands of years.

The teeps appeared by accident. But they solved the most pressing problem the Free Union faced: the detection and punishment of disloyalty. The teeps were invaluable to the Government of the Free Union—and the teeps knew it.

“You got this?” Ross asked, tapping the hood.

Abbud nodded. “Yes.”

The youth was following his thoughts, not his spoken words. Ross flushed angrily. “What was the man like?” he demanded harshly. “The memo plate gives no details.”

“Doctor Franklin is his name. Director of the Federal Resources Commission. Sixty-seven years of age. Here on a visit to a relative.”

“Walter Franklin! I’ve heard of him.” Ross stared up at Abbud. “Then you already—”

“As soon as I removed the hood I was able to scan him.”

“Where did Franklin go after the assault?”

“Indoors. Instructed by the police.”

“After the hood had been taken, of course. It went perfectly. Franklin was spotted by another telepath, not myself. I was informed Franklin was coming my way. When he reached me I shouted that he was wearing a hood. A crowd collected and others took up the shout. The other telepath arrived and we manipulated the crowd until we were near him. I took the hood myself—and you know the rest.”

Ross was silent for a moment. “Do you know how he got the hood? Did you scan that?”

“He received it by mail.”

“Does he—”

“He has no idea who sent it or where it came from.”

Ross frowned. “Then he can’t give us any information about them. The senders.”

“The Hood Makers,” Abbud said icily.

Ross glanced quickly up. “What?”

“The Hood Makers. Somebody makes them.” Abbud’s face was hard. “Somebody is making probe screens to keep us out.”

“And you’re sure—”

“Franklin knows nothing! He arrived in the city last night. This morning his mail machine brought the hood. For a time he deliberated. Then he purchased a hat and put it on over the hood. He set out on foot toward his niece’s house. We spotted him several minutes later, when he entered range.”

“There seem to be more of them, these days. More hoods being sent out. But you know that.” Ross set his jaw. “We’ve got to locate the senders.”

“It’ll take time. They apparently wear hoods constantly.” Abbud’s face twisted. “We have to get so damn close! Our scanning range is extremely limited. But sooner or later we’ll locate one of them. Sooner or later we’ll tear a hood off somebody—and find him . . . ”

“In the last year five thousand hood-wearers have been detected,” Ross stated. “Five thousand -and not one of them knows anything. Where the hoods come from or who makes them.”

“When there are more of us, we’ll have a better chance,” Abbud said grimly. “Right now there are too few of us. But eventually—”

“You’re going to have Franklin probed, aren’t you?” Peters said to Ross. “As a matter of course.”

“I suppose so.” Ross nodded to Abbud. “You might as well go ahead on him. Have one of your group run the regular total probe and see if there’s anything of interest buried down in his non-conscious neural area. Report the results to me in the usual way.”

Abbud reached into his coat. He brought out a tape spool and tossed it down on the desk in front of Ross. “Here you are.”

“What’s this?”

“The total probe on Franklin. All levels—completely searched and recorded.”

Ross stared up at the youth. “You—”

“We went ahead with it.” Abbud moved toward the door. “It’s a good job. Cummings did it. We found considerable disloyalty. Mostly ideological rather than overt. You’ll probably want to pick him up. When he was twenty-four he found some old books and musical records. He was strongly influenced. The latter part of the tape discusses fully our evaluation of his deviation.”

The door melted and Abbud left.

Ross and Peters stared after him. Finally Ross took the tape spool and put it with the bent metal hood.

“I’ll be damned,” Peters said. “They went ahead with the probe.”

Ross nodded, deep in thought. “Yeah. And I’m not sure I like it.”

The two men glanced at each other—and knew, as they did so, that outside the office Ernest Abbud was scanning their thoughts.

“Damn it!” Ross said futilely. “Damn it!”

Walter Franklin breathed rapidly, peering around him. He wiped nervous sweat from his lined face with a trembling hand.

He had got away from the mob—spared for a while. That was four hours ago. Now the sun had set and evening was settling over greater New York. He had managed to make his way half across the city, almost to the outskirts—and now a public alarm was out for his arrest.

Why? He had worked for the Free Union Government all his life. He had done nothing disloyal. Nothing, except open the morning mail, find the hood, deliberate about it, and finally put it on. He remembered the small instruction tag:

GREETINGS!

This probe screen is sent to you with the compliments of the maker and the earnest hope that it will be of some value to you. Thank you.

Nothing else. No other information. For a long time he had pondered. Should he wear it? He had never done anything. He had nothing to hide—nothing disloyal to the Union. But the thought fascinated him. If he wore the hood his mind would be his own. Nobody could look into it. His mind would belong to him again, private, secret, to think as he wished, endless thoughts for no one else’s consumption but his own.

Finally he had made up his mind and put on the hood, fitting his old Homburg over it. He had gone outside—and within ten minutes a mob was screaming and yelling around him. And now a general alarm was out for his arrest.

Franklin wracked his brain desperately. What could he do? They could bring him up before a Clearance Board. No accusation would be brought: it would be up to him to clear himself, to prove he was loyal. Had he ever done anything wrong? Was there something he had done he was forgetting? He had put on the hood. Maybe that was it. There was some sort of an Anti-Immunity bill up in Congress to make wearing of a probe screen a felony, but it hadn’t been passed yet -

The Clearance agents were near, almost on him. He retreated down the corridor of the hotel, glancing desperately around him. A red sign glowed: EXIT. He hurried toward it and down a flight of basement stairs, out onto a dark street. It was bad to be outside, where the mobs were. He had tried to remain indoors as much as possible. But now there was no choice.

Behind him a voice shrilled loudly. Something cut past him, smoking away a section of the pavement. A Slem-ray. Franklin ran, gasping for breath, around a corner and down a side street. People glanced at him curiously as he rushed past.

He crossed a busy street and moved with a surging group of theater goers. Had the agents seen him? He peered nervously around. None in sight.

At the corner he crossed with the lights. He reached the safety zone in the center, watching a sleek Clearance car cruising toward him. Had it seen him go out to the safety zone? He left the zone, heading toward the curb on the far side. The Clearance car shot suddenly forward, gaining speed. Another appeared, coming the other way.

Franklin reached the curb.

The first car ground to a halt. Clearance agents piled out, swarming up onto the sidewalk.

He was trapped. There was no place to hide. Around him tired shoppers and office workers gazed curiously, their faces devoid of sympathy. A few grinned at him in vacant amusement. Franklin peered frantically around. No place, no door, no person -

A car pulled up in front of him, its doors sliding open. “Get in.” A young girl leaned toward him, her pretty face urgent. “Get in, damn it!”

He got in. The girl slammed the doors and the car picked up speed. A Clearance car swung in ahead of them, its sleek bulk blocking the street. A second Clearance car moved in behind them.

The girl leaned forward, gripping the controls. Abruptly the car lifted. It left the street, clearing the cars ahead, gaining altitude rapidly. A flash of violet lit up the sky behind them.

Franklin settled back, mopping his forehead shakily. “Thanks,” he muttered.

“Don’t mention it.” The girl increased the car’s speed. They were leaving the business section of the city, moving above the residential outskirts. She steered silently, intent on the sky ahead.

“Who are you?” Franklin asked.

The girl tossed something back to him. “Put that on.”

A hood. Franklin unfastened it and slipped it awkwardly over his head. “It’s in place.”

“Otherwise they’ll get us with a teep scan. We have to be careful all the time.”

“Where are we going?”

The girl turned to him, studying him with calm gray eyes, one hand resting on the wheel. “We’re going to the Hood Maker,” she said. “The public alarm for you is top priority. If I let you off you won’t last an hour.”

“But I don’t understand.” Franklin shook his head, dazed. “Why do they want me? What have I done?”

“You’re being framed.” The girl brought the car around in a wide arc, wind whistling shrilly through its struts and fenders. “Framed by the teeps. Things are happening fast. There’s no time to lose.”

The little bald-headed man removed his glasses and held out his hand to Franklin, peering near-sightedly. “I’m glad to meet you, Doctor. I’ve followed your work at the Board with great interest.”

“Who are you?” Franklin demanded.

The little man grinned self-consciously. “I’m James Cutter. The Hood Maker, as the teeps call me. This is our factory.” He waved around the room. “Take a look at it.”

Franklin gazed around him. He was in a warehouse, an ancient wooden building of the last century. Giant worm-scored beams rose up, dry and cracking. The floor was concrete. Old-fashioned fluorescent lights glinted and flickered from the roof. The walls were streaked with water stains and bulging pipes.

Franklin moved across the room, Cutter beside him. He was bewildered. Everything had happened fast. He seemed to be outside New York, in some dilapidated industrial suburb. Men were working on all sides of him, bent over stampers and molds. The air was hot. An archaic fan whirred. The warehouse echoed and vibrated with a constant din.

“This—” Franklin murmured. “This is—”

“This is where we make the hoods. Not very impressive, is it? Later on we hope to move to new quarters. Come along and I’ll show you the rest.”

Cutter pushed a side door open and they entered a small laboratory, bottles and retorts everywhere in cluttered confusion. “We do our research in here. Pure and applied. We’ve learned a few things. Some we may use, some we hope won’t be needed. And it keeps our refugees busy.”

“Refugees?”

Cutter pushed some equipment back and seated himself on a lab table. “Most of the others are here for the same reason as you. Framed by the teeps. Accused of deviation. But we got to them first.”

“But why—”

“Why were you framed? Because of your position. Director of a Government Department. All these men were prominent—and all were framed by teep probes.” Cutter lit a cigarette, leaning back against the water-stained wall. “We exist because of a discovery made ten years ago in a Government lab.” He tapped his hood. “This alloy—opaque to probes. Discovered by accident, by one of these men. Teeps came after him instantly, but he escaped. He made a number of hoods and passed them to other workers in his field. That’s how we got started.”

“How many are here?”

Cutter laughed. “Can’t tell you that. Enough to turn out hoods and keep them circulating. To people prominent in Government. People holding positions of authority. Scientists, officials, educators—”

“Because we want to get them first, before the teeps. We got to you too late. A total probe report had already been made out on you, before the hood was even in the mail.

“The teeps are gradually getting a stranglehold over the Government. They’re picking off the best men, denouncing them and getting them arrested. If a teep says a man is disloyal Clearance has to haul him in. We tried to get a hood to you in time. The report couldn’t be passed on to Clearance if you were wearing a hood. But they outsmarted us. They got a mob after you and snatched the hood. As soon as it was off they served the report to Clearance.”

“So that’s why they wanted it off.”

“The teeps can’t file a framed report on a man whose mind is opaque to probes. Clearance isn’t that stupid. The teeps have to get the hoods off. Every man wearing a hood is a man out of bounds. They’ve managed so far by stirring up mobs—but that’s ineffectual. Now they’re working on this bill in Congress. Senator Waldo’s Anti-Immunity Bill. It would outlaw wearing hoods.” Cutter grinned ironically. “If a man is innocent why shouldn’t he want his mind probed? The bill makes wearing a probe shield a felony. People who receive hoods will turn them over to Clearance. There won’t be a man in ten thousand who’ll keep his hood, if it means prison and confiscation of property.”

“I met Waldo, once. I can’t believe he understands what his bill would do. If he could be made to see—”

“Exactly! If he could be made to see. This bill has to be stopped. If it goes through we’re licked. And the teeps are in. Somebody has to talk to Waldo and make him see the situation.” Cutter’s eyes were bright. “You know the man. He’ll remember you.”

“What do you mean?”

“Franklin, we’re sending you back again—to meet Waldo. It’s our only chance to stop the bill. And it has to be stopped.”

The cruiser roared over the Rockies, brush and tangled forest flashing by below. “There’s a level pasture over to the right,” Cutter said. “I’ll set her down, if I can find it.”

He snapped off the jets. The roar died into silence. They were coasting above the hills.

“To the right,” Franklin said.

Cutter brought the cruiser down in a sweeping glide. “This will put us within walking distance of Waldo’s estate. We’ll go the rest of the way on foot.” A shuddering growl shook them as the landing fins dug into the ground—and they were at rest.

Around them tall trees moved faintly with the wind. It was mid-morning. The air was cool and thin. They were high up, still in the mountains, on the Colorado side.

“What are the chances of our reaching him?” Franklin asked.

“Not very good.”

Franklin started. “Why? Why not?”

Cutter pushed the cruiser door back and leaped out onto the ground. “Come on.” He helped Franklin out and slammed the door after him. “Waldo is guarded. He’s got a wall of robots around him. That’s why we’ve never tried before. If it weren’t crucial we wouldn’t be trying now.”

They left the pasture, making their way down the hill along a narrow weed-covered path. “What are they doing it for?” Franklin asked. “The teeps. Why do they want to get power?”

“Human nature, I suppose.”

“Human nature?”

“The teeps are no different from the Jacobins, the Roundheads, the Nazis, the Bolsheviks. There’s always some group that wants to lead mankind—for its own good, of course.”

“Do the teeps believe that?”

“Most teeps believe they’re the natural leaders of mankind. Non-telepathic humans are an inferior species. Teeps are the next step, homo superior. And because they’re superior, it’s natural they should lead. Make all the decisions for us.”

“And you don’t agree,” Franklin said.

“Who should lead mankind, then?” Franklin asked. “Who should be the leaders?”

“Nobody should lead mankind. It should lead itself.” Cutter leaned forward suddenly, body tense.

“We’re almost there. Waldo’s estate is directly ahead. Get ready. Everything depends on the next few minutes.”

“A few robot guards.” Cutter lowered his binoculars. “But that’s not what’s worrying me. If Waldo has a teep nearby, he’ll detect our hoods.”

“And we can’t take them off.”

“No. The whole thing would be out, passed from teep to teep.” Cutter moved cautiously forwards. “The robots will stop us and demand identification. We’ll have to count on your Director’s clip.”

They left the bushes, crossing the open field toward the buildings that made up Senator Waldo’s estate. They came onto a dirt road and followed it, neither of them speaking, watching the landscape ahead.

“Halt!” A robot guard appeared, streaking toward them across the field. “Identify yourselves!”

Franklin showed his clip. “I’m Director level. We’re here to see the Senator. I’m an old friend.”

Automatic relays clicked as the robot studied the identification clip. “From the Director level?”

“That’s right,” Franklin said, becoming uneasy.

“Get out of the way,” Cutter said impatiently. “We don’t have any time to waste.”

The robot withdrew uncertainly. “Sorry to have stopped you, sir. The Senator is inside the main building. Directly ahead.”

“All right.” Cutter and Franklin advanced past the robot. Sweat stood out on Cutter’s round face. “We made it,” he murmured. “Now let’s hope there aren’t any teeps inside.”

Franklin reached the porch. He stepped slowly up, Cutter behind him. At the door he halted, glancing at the smaller man. “Shall I—”

“Go ahead.” Cutter was tense. “Let’s get right inside. It’s safer.”

Franklin raised his hand. The door clicked sharply as its lens photographed him and checked his image. Franklin prayed silently. If the Clearance alarm had been sent out this far -

The door melted.

“Inside,” Cutter said quickly.

Franklin entered, looking around in the semi-darkness. He blinked, adjusting to the dim light of the hall. Somebody was coming toward him. A shape, a small shape, coming rapidly, lithely. Was it Waldo?

A lank, sallow-faced youth entered the hall, a fixed smile on his face. “Good morning, Doctor Franklin,” he said. He raised his Slem-gun and fired.

Cutter and Ernest Abbud stared down at the oozing mass that had been Doctor Franklin. Neither of them spoke. Finally Cutter raised his hand, his face drained of color.

“Was that necessary?”

Abbud shifted, suddenly conscious of him. “Why not?” He shrugged, the Slem-gun pointed at Cutter’s stomach. “He was an old man. He wouldn’t have lasted long in the protective-custody camp.”

Cutter took out his package of cigarettes and lit up slowly, his eyes on the youth’s face. He had never seen Ernest Abbud before. But he knew who he was. He watched the sallow-faced youth kick idly at the remains on the floor.

“Then Waldo is a teep,” Cutter said.

“Yes.”

“Franklin was wrong. He does have full understanding of his bill.”

Cutter hesitated. He dropped his cigarette thoughtfully to the floor and crushed it underfoot. “What are you doing here? You usually hang out in New York. This is a long way out here.”

Abbud smiled. “We picked up Doctor Franklin’s thoughts as he entered the girl’s car—before she gave him the hood. She waited too long. We got a distinct visual image of her, seen from the back seat, of course. But she turned around to give him the hood. Two hours ago Clearance picked her up. She knew a great deal—our first real contact. We were able to locate the factory and round up most of the workers.”

“Oh?” Cutter murmured.

“They’re in protective custody. Their hoods are gone—and the supply stored for distribution. The stampers have been dismantled. As far as I know we have all the group. You’re the last one.”

“Then does it matter if I keep my hood?”

Abbud’s eyes flickered. “Take it off. I want to scan you—Mister Hood Maker.”

Cutter grunted. “What do you mean?”

“Several of your men gave us images of you—and details of your trip here. I came out personally, notifying Waldo through our relay system in advance. I wanted to be here myself.”

“Why?”

“It’s an occasion. A great occasion.”

“What position do you hold?” Cutter demanded.

Abbud’s sallow face turned ugly. “Come on! Off with the hood! I could blast you now. But I want to scan you first.”

“All right. I’ll take it off. You can scan me, if you want. Probe all the way down.” Cutter paused, reflecting soberly. “It’s your funeral.”

“What do you mean?”

Cutter removed his hood, tossing it onto a table by the door. “Well? What do you see? What do I know --that none of the others knew?”

For a moment Abbud was silent.

Suddenly his face twitched, his mouth working. The Slem-gun swayed. Abbud staggered, a violent shudder leaping through his lank frame. He gaped at Cutter in rising horror.

“I learned it only recently,” Cutter said. “In our lab. I didn’t want to use it—but you forced me to take off my hood. I always considered the alloy my most important discovery—until this. In some ways, this is even more important. Don’t you agree?”

Abbud said nothing. His face was a sickly gray. His lips moved but no sound came.

“I had a hunch—and I played it for all it was worth. I knew you telepaths were born from a single group, resulting from an accident—the Madagascar hydrogen explosion. That made me think. Most mutants, that we know of, are thrown off universally by the species that’s reached the mutation stage. Not a single group in one area. The whole world, wherever the species exists.

“Damage to the germ plasma of a specific group of humans is the cause of your existence. You weren’t a mutant in the sense that you represented a natural development of the evolutionary process. In no sense could it be said that homo sapiens had reached the mutation stage. So perhaps you weren’t a mutant.

“I began to make studies, some biological, some merely statistical. Sociological research. We began correlating facts on you, on each member of your group we could locate. How old you were. What you were doing for a living. How many were married. Number of children. After a while I came across the facts you’re scanning right now.”

Cutter leaned toward Abbud, watching the youth intently.

“You’re not a true mutant, Abbud. Your group exists because of a chance explosion. You’re different from us because of damage to the reproductive apparatus of your parents. You lack one specific characteristic that true mutants possess.” A faint smile twitched across Cutter’s features. “A lot of you are married. But not one birth has been reported. Not one birth! Not a single teep child! You can’t

“You’re not mutants. You’re freaks!”

Abbud grunted hoarsely, his body trembling. “I see this, in your mind.” He pulled himself together with an effort. “And you’ve kept this secret, have you? You’re the only one who knows?”

“Somebody else knows,” Cutter said.

“Who?”

“You know. You scanned me. And since you’re a teep, all the others—”

Abbud fired, the Slem-gun digging frantically into his own middle. He dissolved, showering in a rain of fragments. Cutter moved back, his hands over his face. He closed his eyes, holding his breath.

When he looked again there was nothing.

Cutter shook his head. “Too late, Abbud. Not fast enough. Scanning is instant—and Waldo is within range. The relay system . . . And even if they missed you, they can’t avoid picking me up.”

A sound. Cutter turned. Clearance agents were moving rapidly into the hall, glancing down at the remains on the floor and up at Cutter.

Director Ross covered Cutter uncertainly, confused and shaken. “What happened here? Where—”

“Scan him!” Peters snapped. “Get a teep in here quick. Bring Waldo in. Find out what happened.”

Cutter grinned ironically. “Sure,” he said, nodding shakily. He sagged with relief. “Scan me. I have nothing to hide. Get a teep in here for a probe—if you can find any . . . ”

Notes

Philip K. Dick The Hood Maker (“Immunity”) 1/26/53. Imagination, June 1955.